Guide to the South Africa Now Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
South Africa Now collection
1978-1994
1988-1991
MS 1818
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
319.01
(2,512 boxes)
The collection consists of videotapes and a small number of transcripts, log books, and publicity files relating to the television program South Africa Now, produced by Globalvision from 1988 to 1991. It includes a nearly complete run of tapes of the approximately 150 newscasts produced during the three year run of the program as well as approximately 2000 tapes of interviews, short reports, documentaries, stock footage, and other footage used in the program's production. The show documents various aspects of South African politics, government, and culture during the final years of apartheid.
Globalvision, Inc
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Globalvision, 2003.
Existence and Location of Copies
The entire collection, with the exception of the paper files in boxes 2384-2391, is available in digital form through Manuscripts and Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection, with the exception of the paper files in boxes 2384-2391, is digitized. Researchers must use the digital copies instead of the originals.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
The television news program South Africa Now first aired in April 1988. The program actively sought to fill a perceived void in news coverage of South Africa and the anti-apartheid movement in particular, stemming from media censorship measures instituted by the South African government in 1986. Produced by Globalvision, Inc., a television production company founded in 1987 by Rory O'Connor and Danny Schechter to focus on global human rights issues, South Africa Now ran weekly on public television stations throughout the United States and in fifteen other countries. Segments of the program occasionally received even wider distribution when they were aired on the CNN's Weekly World Report.
The program covered South African news, produced background and investigative reports on the affairs of South Africa and neighboring states, and provided cultural features documenting South African theater, musicians, writers, and artists. In the three years it ran, the program covered a highly turbulent era in South African history that saw severe repression of black and colored South Africans, the release of Nelson Mandela from prison, and the end of the apartheid system. Because its reporters and producers were not welcome in South Africa, the show relied primarily on material culled from the South African news, European sources, and footage shot by independent producers in South Africa and smuggled out of the country. Regular anchors, reporters, and other contributors included Carolyn Craven, Fana Kakana, Thandeka Gqubule, Mweli Mzizi, Phillip Tomlinson, Joseph Diescho, and Eric Nadler.
Globalvision ceased production of South Africa Now in April 1991, due to lack of operating funds. Shortly before the last show aired, Globalvision, Inc. received a George Polk Award for Journalistic Excellence in recognition of South Africa Now.
Arrangement
Arranged in eighteen series: I. Episodes, 1988-1991; II. Short Reports, circa 1985-1991; III. Documentaries, 1980-1991; IV. Stock Footage, circa 1987-1990; V. Interviews, circa 1978-1991; VI. Cultural Tapes, circa 1979-1991; VII. American Protest, 1986-1991; VIII. Other Network Footage, 1985-1991; IX. Jesse Jackson Diaries, 1986; X. United Nations TV, 1988-1989; XI. Stills, circa 1988-1990; XII. Miscellaneous PAL Tapes, 1984-1990; XIII. Mandela in America, 1990; XIV. South African Tourism Board, 1983-1988, undated; XV. Footage from Independent Producers from South Africa, 1984-1989; XVI. South African Footage, 1989-1990; XVII. Reports about South Africa Now, circa 1988-1991; XVIII. Miscellaneous Unnumbered Tapes, 1987-circa 1990; XIX. Paper Logs and Publicity Files, circa 1988-1994.
General
This collection was digitized through the generous support of the Arcadia Foundation.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of videotapes and a small number of transcripts, log books, and publicity files relating to the television program South Africa Now, produced by Globalvision from 1988 to 1991. It includes a nearly complete run of tapes of the approximately 150 newscasts produced during the three year run of the program as well as approximately 2000 tapes of interviews, short reports, documentaries, stock footage, and other footage used in the program's production.
The collection includes visual documentation of the final years of apartheid in South Africa and includes interviews with and other significant footage of anti-apartheid leaders, including Nelson Mandela, Winnie Mandela, Desmond Tutu, Walter Sisulu, Albertina Sisulu, Albie Sachs, Joe Slovo, Thabo Mbeki, Allan Boesak, Oliver Tambo, Beyers Naude, and many others. It also documents the activities of the South African government and its leaders, particularly P.W. Botha and F. W. De Klerk. Many organizations also receive extensive coverage, such as the African National Congress (ANC), the Congress of South African Trade Unions (COSATU), and the South-West African Peoples Organization (SWAPO). Many editions of the program included the segment "Frontline Focus," which reported the news in the southern African states of Angola, Namibia, Zambia, Zimbabwe, and Mozambique. South Africa Now produced at least one cultural segment per show. The collection, therefore, contains footage of South African artists, playwrights, musicians, authors, and filmmakers, including Athol Fugard, Hugh Masakela, Ladysmith Black Mambazo, Mzwakhe Mbuli, Johnny Klegg, Gcina Mhlopher, Peter Magubane, and Nadine Gordimer. Finally, the collection documents the activities of the international anti-apartheid movement that put political and economic pressure on South Africa to end the system of apartheid.
Appraisal
Box 2370, Tape T1, McNeil/Lehrer NewsHour report on South Africa Now, 1988 Oct 26, was unplayable and removed from the collection.
Anti-apartheid movements -- South Africa; Anti-apartheid movements; Apartheid -- South Africa; Human rights -- Abuse of -- South Africa; Human rights -- South Africa; Investigative reporting -- South Africa; Television programs -- South Africa; South Africa -- Politics and government; Video recordings; South Africa Now (Television program); Boesak, Allan, 1945-; Botha, P. W. (Pieter Willem), 1916-2006; De Klerk, F. W. (Frederik Willem), 1936-; Fugard, Athol, 1932-; Gordimer, Nadine, 1923-2014; Jackson, Jesse, 1941-; Magubane, Peter, 1932-; Mandela, Nelson, 1918-2013; Mandela, Winnie, 1936-2018; Masekela, Hugh, 1939-2018; Mbeki, Thabo, 1942-; Naudé, Beyers, 1915-2004; Sachs, Albie, 1935-; Sisulu, Albertina, 1918-2011; Sisulu, Walter, 1912-2003; Tambo, Oliver, 1917-1993; Tutu, Desmond, 1931-; African National Congress; Cosatu; Globalvision, Inc; South African Tourism Board; SWAPO; United Nations
- Episodes, 1988-1991; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series conatins full episodes of South Africa Now, arranged by season. Transcripts are filed at the end of the series.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Materials in this series are digitized. Researchers must use the digital copies instead of the originals.
  - First Season
    - Episode 1, 1988; 1 (Box 1)
      The episode includes: popular education in South African townships; campaign to release children from prison for Christmas; South African government music video, done in response to "Sun City" and "We Are the World," an interracial propaganda ploy that failed.
    - Episode 2, 1988; 1 (Box 2)
      The episode includes: "Black on Black Violence," a look at Pretoria's use of vigilante squads in stirring up violence in the townships; how the South African government wants the world to see it, with excerpts from an official tourism film, Love Changes People and People Change Things.
    - Episode 3, 1988; 1 (Box 3)
      The episode includes: torture of children in detention with preview of an English documentary featuring testimony of children released from prison and conflict footage never seen before on United States television; video report on the funeral of the slain France African National Congress (ANC) representative, Dulcie September, in Paris; report on death of writer Alan Paton; excerpts from the visit of the cast of the hit Broadway show, Sarafina, to the United Nations; a look at the vote on sanctions; Pretoria's stance, with more highlights from a South African government-financed film.
      Extraneous, non-episode footage included at end of the tape.
    - Episode 4, 1988; 1 (Box 4)
      The episode includes: the "Press Ban," a report from Afravision inside South Africa on how black journalists cover the news in the townships; South Africa Now interview with a visiting township reporter; analysis of the background to killings of ANC officials from Jennifer Davis of the American Committee on Africa and William Johnston of Episcopal Churchpeople for a Free Southern Africa; Pretoria's position, with excerpts of a widely distributed anti-ANC film, A Time for Candor, with commentary by Jennifer Davis.
    - Episode 5, 1988; 1 (Box 5)
      The episode includes: sanctions and reform, conflicting views on the sanctions debate and analysis of the government's "reform" program with Mark Swelling, a Johannesburg-based political analyst and contributor to The Weekly Mail and Bobby Godsell, labor negotiator for the Anglo-American Corporation; report from inside South Africa on a diverse range of views from black South Africans on sanctions.
    - Episode 6, 1988; 1 (Box 6)
      The episode includes: Bishop Tutu in America and highlights from his sermon at New York's Riverside Church, with excerpts from a major press conference; report from inside South Africa on the growing conflict between the church and the state; Bishop Tutu singing freedom songs.
    - Episode 7, 1988; 1 (Box 7)
      The episode includes: Namibia, interview with Sam Nujoma, President of the South West African People's Organization (SWAPO), with highlights from an English documentary for background, and further analysis, in an interview with Damu Smith, director of the Washington Office on Africa, of the implications of the Angola-South Africa negotiations; Miriam Mekeba's comeback with statements and music from "Mama Africa," South Africa's leading singer.
    - Episode 8, 1988; 1 (Box 8)
      The episode includes: the war in Mozambique with eyewitness testimony by two doctors who have worked in Mozambique for many years; background reports from two films: Alliance in Action, produced by UNICEF and narrated by Harry Belafonte, and Frontline South Africa: Destructive Engagement; interview with Mary De Almeida of Children's Fund for Southern Africa (CHISA); the A.F.R.I.C.A. video in which rappers support the front-line state, with report on the video's origins by Jesse Jackson.
    - Episode 9, 1988; 1 (Box 9)
      The episode includes: whites against apartheid, with interviews with Dennis Goldberg, leader of the African National Congress on trial with Nelson Mandela in 1963 and imprisoned for twenty-two years, and Nina Overton, a prominent Afrikaner academic; activities of the UDF and Black Sash in reaching out to whites; excerpt from a documentary on Beyers Naudé, an Afrikaner minister who became an anti-apartheid activist; Johnny Clegg and Savuka, a "rockumentary" on South Africa's best known multi-racial band.
    - Episode 10, 1988; 1 (Box 10)
      The episode includes: political bannings and new press restrictions inside South Africa; a three-day labor stay-away in June that brought the country to a virtual standstill; the American censorship of the Nelson Mandela concert in London, with an interview with Little Steven who explains the "cleansing" of political message in the Mandela concert by American television; report on political repression in South Africa, with interviews with Miriam Jacobs of Human Rights Watch and Eric Goldstein of The Committee to Protect Journalists; the Freedom Beat Fest in Central Park.
    - Episode 11, 1988; 1 (Box 11)
      The episode includes: the war in Angola with an exclusive interview with United States- and South Africa-backed Unia?o Nacional para a Independe?ncia Total de Angola (UNITA) leader, Jonas Savimbi, and interviews with American black activists Benjamin Chavis and Elombe Brathe; report on the Angolan-South African conflict with recent footage from the frontline by independent television journalist, Jon Alpert; Senegal's top musician, Youssou N'Dour, singing for South Africa,
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 11D)
    - Episode 12, 1988; 1 (Box 12)
      The episode includes: Nelson Mandela turns seventy in prison; American premiere of a new film, Remembering Mandela, by Peter Davis; a report on the negotiations between Angola, South Africa, Cuba. and the United States to end the war in Angola, with an interview with Phillip van Niekirk, South African correspondent for The Boston Globe; a report on Zwelakhe Sisulu, editor of The New Nation, who was recently transferred from prison to a Johannesburg hospital; interview with Tony Weaver, South African journalist, on the new press restrictions in South Africa; premiere of new short video pieces in tribute to Nelson Mandela from the Institute for Contemporary Art in London; Special AKA sings for the release of Nelson Mandela.
    - Episode 13, 1988; 1 (Box 13)
      The episode includes: worldwide commemorations of Nelson Mandela's seventieth birthday; exclusive footage of Winnie Mandela's press conference in Johannesburg; interview with Paul David, leader of South Africa's Indian Congress, on the unlikely release of Nelson Mandela; footage of the New York birthday celebration in Central Park; excerpt from the Reverend Jesse Jackson's speech at the Democratic National Convention on the party's unified stance on South Africa: analysis by Africa Report contributing editor Michael Maren on the Angolan negotiations; South Africa's defense force under threat, both on the Angolan battlefield and at home, including an interview with Heinz Klug, an exiled South African journalist who speaks on White South African's "End Conscription" campaign; Sakhile, one of South Africa's most popular jazz bands, plays at the Rainbow Club outside of Durban in honor of Nelson Mandela.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 13D)
    - Episode 14, 1988; 1 (Box 13)
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 14D)
    - Episode 15, 1988; 1 (Box 14)
    - Episode 16, 1988; 1 (Box 15)
  - Second Season
    - Episode 101, 1988; 1 (Box 16)
      The episode includes: Tony Weaver reports from Capetown on government crackdown; three United Democratic Front (UDF) leaders take refuge in United States consulate in Johannesburg; Reverend Allan Boesak on foreign media in South Africa; Cuban documentary of fighting in Angola; South Africa's hottest band, Savuka, and its star, Johnny Clegg.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 16D)
    - Episode 102, 1988; 1 (Box 17)
      The episode includes: P.W. Botha meets with Zaire's President Mobutu; interview with Gwen Lister, editor of The Namibian; bomb destroys headquarters of anti-apartheid church leaders; exclusive television preview of new film about Broadway hit.
    - Episode 103, 1988; 1 (Box 18)
      The episode includes: "White Wolves" firebomb The Namibian; bombing of Khanya House, headquarters of the Catholic Bishops Conference; "Shell Shocked," the WBCN radio Boston campaign against Royal Dutch Shell; the New York Times misreads progress on Angolan negotiations; David Turnley, photojournalist, expelled from South Africa.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 18D)
    - Episode 104, 1988; 1 (Box 19)
      The episode includes: government threatens to silence opposition newspaper Weekly Mail; medical report on detained New Nation editor Zwelakhe Sisulu; analysis of South African elections; Izulu Dance Theatre.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 19D)
    - Episode 105, 1988; 1 (Box 20)
      The episode includes: results of South African elections; P.W. Botha meets with African leaders; South African police seize film on Namibia in final stage of production; U.S. presidential candidates' positions on South Africa; Ladysmith Black Mambazo.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 20D)
    - Episode 106, 1988; 1 (Box 21)
      The episode includes: the Weekly Mail is shut down; Canadian Broadcasting report on South African press censorship; Japan quits importing uranium from South Africa; medical care under apartheid; Mapantsula, South Africa's The Harder They Come.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 21D)
    - Episode 107, 1988; 1 (Box 22)
      The episode includes: bombing of headquarters of the National Union of South African Students; Vrye Weekblad, South Africa's first Afrikaans language opposition newspaper; implications of Bush victory on United States foreign policy toward South Africa; Delmas treason trial; the war in Mozambique.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 22D)
    - Episode 108, 1988; 1 (Box 23)
      The episode includes: analysis of Angolan peace settlement; Delmas treason trial verdict; government threatens to close down Vrye Weekblad; Suffer the Children, documentary on black children under apartheid and a video response from the government; Shaka Zulu controversy.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 23D)
    - Episode 109, 1988; 1 (Box 24)
      The episode includes: update on Nelson Mandela; outcome of trials of the Sharpeville Six; Pat Robertson's 700 Club broadcasts from South Africa; profile of Beyers Naudé, former Bruderbund member turned anti-apartheid activist; growth of indigenous "working class" culture in South Africa.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 24D)
    - Episode 110, 1988; 1 (Box 25)
      The episode includes: exclusive footage of the Amnesty International tour in Zimbabwe; eight political prisoners, including editor of the New Nation released into limited freedom; profile of black township reporters featured in new book, Dateline Soweto; interview with Derek Bauer, cartoonist for the Daily Mail.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 25D)
    - Episode 111, 1988; 1 (Box 26)
      The episode includes: exclusive television footage of "Silver and Gold," song from U2's new film, Rattle and Hum; Nelson Mandela moved from hospital to house on a prison farm; South Africa agrees to finalize Namibia/Angola peace talks; thirty-five arrested in New York at protest criticizing Mobil Oil's involvement in South Africa; AIDS in Africa, criticism of South African documentary.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 26D)
    - Episode 112, 1988; 1 (Box 27)
      The episode includes: review of top ten news stories from southern Africa in 1988; update on continuing press restrictions in South Africa; review of trends for the coming year; history of anti-apartheid anthem, God Bless Africa.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 27D)
    - Episode 113, 1988; 1 (Box 28)
      The episode includes: special: screening of documentary, Artists Against Apartheid.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 28D)
  - Third Season
    - Episode 201, 1989; 1 (Box 29)
      The episode includes: investigative report on the National Religious Broadcasters' links with South Africa; P.W. Botha's stroke and possible replacement candidates; detainees start hunger strike after 1000 days of the state of emergency; analysis of United Nations Resolution 435, the Angola/Namibian settlement; report on South Africa grassroots cultural expression.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 29D)
    - Episode 202, 1989; 1 (Box 30)
      The episode includes: exclusive footage of Jesse Jackson in Africa and report on the "African-American" name controversy; analysis of the various players in the Angolan conflict; "Stetsasonic" rap group works to raise the consciousness of American students; report on Citibank's decision to extend $600 million in loans to South Africa for ten years.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 30D)
    - Episode 203, 1989; 1 (Box 31)
      The episode includes: report on Winnie Mandela and the role of the media in her tragedy; victory of sorts for the detainee hunger strikers; poverty in South Africa, a detailed report on a shocking new study; report on the Soweto rent boycott in progress since 1976.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 31D)
    - Episode 204, 1989; 1 (Box 32)
      The episode includes: report on the restrictions placed on released detainees; update on Winnie Mandela: the fallout: interviews with people on the streets of Johannesburg; report on how SWAPO plans to handle the new government in Namibia; investigative report on the activities of the South African lobby in the United States.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 32D)
    - Episode 205, 1989; 1 (Box 33)
      The episode includes: details of a State Department report on human rights violations in South Africa; United Auto Workers (UAW) support for South Africa's budding labor movement; Winnie Mandela update: possible infiltration into the "football club" by South African police; new Irish documentary, Mozambique: Scene of a Crime.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 33D)
    - Episode 206, 1989; 1 (Box 34)
      The episode includes: report from Namibia: Is the United Nations leaving too much up to the South Africans?; a day of support for hunger strikers in South Africa: reports from Johannesburg and New York; the ANC Video Unit and how they are getting the story out; Africa News (Service?), a small but influential group in Durham, North Carolina, keeps the information flowing.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 34D)
    - Episode 207, 1989; 1 (Box 35)
      The episode includes: hunger strikers near death as protests against detention continue; F.W. Botha vs. P.W. Botha, white politics divided; Israel and South Africa, Bishop Tutu appeals and Israel's Knesset responds; South African music videos.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 35D)
    - Episode 208, 1989; 1 (Box 36)
      The episode includes: Commemorations of the Sharpeville Massacre and update on activities of the Pan Africanist Council (PAC); investigative report on a spy for South Africa: the Dulce case; launch of new weekly segment, Namibia Watch; Mbongeni Ngema, the creator of Sarafina speaks out in an exclusive interview.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 36D)
    - Episode 209, 1989; 1 (Box 37)
      The episode includes: Namibia Watch: the United Nations troops arrive as violence continues; British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher visits South Africa and Zimbabwe; Archbishop Desmond Tutu travels in Nicaragua, a report from Sandinista television; Tony Weaver with an in-depth report on the history of the Namibia situation.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 37D)
    - Episode 210, 1989; 1 (Box 38)
      The episode includes: P.W. Botha steps down; Namibia: an analysis of the two agreements; Jonas Savimbi: "Freedom Fighter or Killer," a special report of charges by former supporters; a festival of South African artists in exile, Culture in Another South Africa.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 38D)
    - Episode 211, 1989; 1 (Box 39)
      The episode includes: new questions from Namibia: how did the SWAPO guerrillas die; children on the frontline; behind Resiste?ncia Nacional Moc?ambicana (RENAMO); township art.
      - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 39D)
    - Episode 212, 1989; 1 (Box 40)